<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The house of God The sure foundation, the stones, the vvorkmen and order of the building. The incomparable strength of that house, and the vaine assaults and batteries of Satan and all his power. In a sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, December 24, 1626. / By Matthevv Brookes.</title>
            <author>Brookes, Matthew, fl. 1626-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16943</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3836</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119308</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854515</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854515</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19941</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16943)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19941)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1196:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The house of God The sure foundation, the stones, the vvorkmen and order of the building. The incomparable strength of that house, and the vaine assaults and batteries of Satan and all his power. In a sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, December 24, 1626. / By Matthevv Brookes.</title>
                  <author>Brookes, Matthew, fl. 1626-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. P[urslowe] for Richard Cartwright, and are to be sold in Ducke-lane, neere Smithfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Marsh's Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19941:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19941:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HOVSE OF GOD. The ſure Foundation, the Stones, the VVorkmen and Order of the Building.</p>
            <p>The incomparable ſtrength of that Houſe, and the vaine aſſaults and batteries of Satan and all his power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a Sermon preached at Pauls Croſſe, December</hi> 24. 1626.</p>
            <p>By MATTHEVV BROOKES.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISA. 33.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Heare yee, that are farre off, what I haue done, and yee that are neere, acknowledge my might.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. P.</hi> for <hi>Richard Cartwright,</hi> and are to be ſold in Ducke-lane, neere Smithfield. 1627.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19941:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19941:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL and truely Religious, HENRY WALLOPE, Knight; the fat of Earth, and the dew of Heauen.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>eneca</hi> will not haue it denyed, that a good Pylot is skilfull, albeit it be on dry land; his reaſon is, becauſe being endowed both with contemplatiue and practicke knowledge, ſo much as may be thought neceſſary both to make him poſitiuely, and comparatiuely ſufficient for that Art he is onely deſtitute of opportunity to bewray his iudgement, and ability. My caſe is iuſt ſo: I muſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely confeſſe my due reſpect euer ſince I was firſt known vnto you, and haue wanted nothing with the good Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, but occaſion to ſhew it; let me this way call the world to witneſſe that I honour you.</p>
            <p>That which put me vpon this Text, was the requeſt of ſome of my friends made vnto me, for ſome reaſons beſt knowne vnto them and me. How I haue anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their expectation, I know not; whatſoeuer this poore
<pb facs="tcp:19941:3"/>diſcourſe ſeemes to be, I ſhall deſire you to accept it with the ſame affection that I beſtow it on you; the gift is too light, if it be waighed againſt your fauours: but I hope you will reſpect the minde and ability of the giuer, imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> who with as ready a hand receiued thoſe few verſes preſented vnto him by a poore <hi>Greeke,</hi> as that great <hi>Arabian</hi> Courſer giuen him by <hi>Titinius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I haue not meddled with any controuerſed points (as the words of the Text ſeeme to promiſe, and as I preſume it was expected) conceiue in charitie that I aimed chiefely at the preſent profit of my hearers: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it had beene ſomewhat too preſumptuous, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the worth of all thoſe who haue both diſputed and written of theſe things. Howſoeuer, let me ſay this place of Scripture to be like vnto that leafe which beareth both the <hi>Antidote</hi> and the <hi>Aconiton:</hi> for certainly our aduerſaries poſſeſſed with the ſpirit of ſlumber, doe moſt vilely abuſe this Text, and are therefore baned in the ſame place were others are preſerued.</p>
            <p>There remaineth nothing, but that I commend you and all yours to God in my prayers, which I will neuer ceaſe to doe, and remaine euer,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours humbly at command, <hi>M. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19941:3"/>
            <head>The Houſe of God.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATTH. 16.18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Thou art Peter, and vpon this Rocke I will build my Church, and the gates of Hell ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He materiall Temple or Houſe which <hi>Salomon</hi> built for the Lord,
<note place="margin">Act. 7.47.</note> was by the ſpeciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God ſituated vpon the Mount <hi>Moriah;</hi> (it was an hard ſtony or rocky hill, Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> euery way, ſaue toward the riſing of the Sunne inacceſſible, on which place <hi>Abraham</hi> being about to offer vp <hi>Iſaak</hi> his onely ſonne,
<note place="margin">Gen. 22.13, 14.</note> becauſe that God prouided a Ramme, which he tooke and <hi>offered vp for a burnt offering in ſtead of his Sonne, he called the name of that place Iehouah-ijreh, as it is ſaid to this day, In the mount of the Lord it ſhall be ſeene:</hi> there was alſo the threſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing floore of <hi>Araunah</hi> the <hi>Iebuſite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.18.</note> in which the Prophet <hi>Gad</hi> commanded King <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>reare an Altar vnto the Lord,</hi> for the appeaſing of his wrath in the time of that great peſtilence,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſeph. antiq. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</note> which he pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued the people withall, becauſe that <hi>Dauid</hi> had
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19941:4"/>numbred them) in that place did King <hi>Salomon</hi> found that magnificent Temple.</p>
            <p>By this a further matter was fitly typed:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Henricus Bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting itinerario Scripturae.</hi> 1 Cor. 10 4</note> for that great Rocke or ſure Foundation was a type of Chriſt: and as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of that Rocke, which gaue drinke to the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Deſart, that that Rocke was <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that is to ſay, a figure of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caluin. Com. in</hi> 1 <hi>Cor. cap.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 4. Iſa. 28.16.</note> becauſe it ſignified <hi>Chriſt, that ſtone, that try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtone, that precious corner ſtone, that ſure Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the Lord God layed in Sion.</hi> Vpon him if we offer vp our prayers to God, they ſhall ſurely be accepted, as <hi>Abrahams</hi> and <hi>Dauids</hi> ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>Further the Temple founded on that Rocke, was a figure of the Church built on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for he is that ſure Foundation vpon which it ſtandeth, like that houſe whereon the raine <hi>deſcended, and the floods came,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.24.</note> 
               <hi>and the winds blew, and beat vpon that houſe, and it fell not, for it was founded vpon a Rocke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This great myſtery was little perceiued by the Iewes, whom foure ſpecious titles cauſed to fwell with pride. The firſt was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the people: for they ſuppoſed themſelues to bee the peculiar people of God; holy by propagation from <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> to whom God had ſo bound himſelfe, that he could not (<hi>ex pacto &amp; iuſtitia,</hi> by vertue of his coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Iuſtice) forſake them, and therefore they boaſted,
<note place="margin">Iohn 8.39.</note> ſaying, <hi>Abraham is our father.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Law, for they attributed ſo much to the Law, eſpecially to the Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies thereof, that they boaſted themſelues to be made righteous by them, (for that they duly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued them) and no leſſe the friends of God then
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19941:4"/>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> was. It was reputed as a capitall crime in <hi>Stephen,</hi> that he ſpake of the diſſoluing of that Temple, and the aboliſhing of thoſe <hi>Moſaicall</hi> cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies:
<note place="margin">Act. 6.13.</note> 
               <hi>This man ceaſeth not to ſpeake blaſphemous words againſt this holy place and the Law.</hi> The third was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Temple: for they vainely dreamed that God was therewith ſo highly pleaſed, that he would neuer admit any other place of worſhip: therefore when the Prophets threatned euils vpon them for their ſins, they would oppoſe their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple againſt all inconueniences:
<note place="margin">Hic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 7.4.</note> 
               <hi>The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord.</hi> The fourth was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the place: their whole Land, (as they ſuppoſed) God had elected ſo, to place his Name there, that he would accept no ſeruice in any other place: carnally did they vnderſtand thoſe words of the Prophet, <hi>In Iudah is God knowne;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 76.1.</note> 
               <hi>his Name is great in Iſrael:</hi> as if God were neither knowne, nor to be knowne in any place elſe. But God denyed to be ſo bound vnto them, where hee threatned not to ſpare them for the place ſake.
<note place="margin">Hier. 7.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>How much theſe men deceiued themſelues, and became vaine in their owne imaginations, may be ſeene by <hi>Chriſt</hi> his reply to an anſwer made by the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> to a queſtion propoſed by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. For when as Chriſt, in the third yeere of his Miniſtrie, which was the 33. yeere of his age,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>An. Oſiand. Harm. Euang. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 32.</note> went the ſecond time vnto the borders of the Gentiles, and vpon the confines of <hi>Caeſarea Philippi,</hi> propounded vnto his Diſciples this queſtion; <hi>Whom doe men ſay that I the ſonne of man am?</hi> and when as hee had receiued their anſwer, reporting
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19941:5"/>the opinions or diuers conceipts which the people had of him;
<note place="margin">Mar. 6.14, 15. Luc. 9.7, 8.</note> ſome giuing out that he was <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> ſome <hi>Elias,</hi> ſome <hi>Hieremias,</hi> or one of the Prophets: Our Sauiour, who was not ignorant of this, (hauing for this purpoſe asked the queſtion) doth from thence take occaſion to come neerer to their conſciences, that ſo he might ſee what good vſe they had made of that heauenly doctrine which hee had taught them, and thoſe diuine Miracles which he had wrought before them; and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand further, ſaying, <hi>Whom ſay ye that I am?</hi> To which propoſition when <hi>Peter</hi> readily replyed, ſaying, <hi>Thou art Chriſt, the Sonne of the liuing God,</hi> hee hath then that he look't for, and taketh occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from thence to cleare the whole matter, and to make it appeare who are his choſen people: by what lawes he will gouerne them: what that buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his might be, which the Temple figured, and that elected place, which he would neuer leaue nor forſake.</p>
            <p>Firſt he aſſureth <hi>Peter,</hi> that the anſwer which he had giuen him, was not <hi>nati ex carne &amp; ſanguine,</hi> the ſenſuall wiſdome of a man borne of fleſh and blood: but <hi>renati ex ſpiritu ſancto,</hi> the heauenly wiſdome of a man borne againe of the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Fleſh and blood hath not reuealed it vnto thee, but my Father which is in heauen.</hi> Secondly, he letteth <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> to vnderſtand, what prerogatiue he had obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, by laying vp in his heart that good leſſon taught him by the Spirit of God: <hi>(viz.)</hi> hee is made a member of that ſpirituall building which Chriſt would to bee built vpon himſelfe, as the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19941:5"/>foundation; the fruite and effect whereof is, that he ſhould neuer fall away from Chriſt to his deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: <hi>And I ſay vnto thee, Thou art Peter, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Rocke will I build my Churh, and the gates of Hell ſhall not preuaile againſt it.</hi> Laſtly, he doth am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifie this prerogatiue, by declaration of that priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which he receiued by his Miniſteriall functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the fruit and effect of the ſame: <hi>And I will giue vnto thee the Keyes of the Kingdome of Heauen; and whatſoeuer thou ſhalt bind on earth, ſhall be bound in Heauen; whatſoeuer thou ſhalt looſe on earth, ſhall be loofed in Heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which I will ſet before you, is the prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue which <hi>Peter</hi> obtained by the faith which he had receiued; the fruite and effect whereof was his good confeſſion: and heerein confider three things: Firſt, his perſonall benefit, <hi>Thou art Peter:</hi> Secondly, whereunto that perſonall benefit hath relation, <hi>viz.</hi> the building: this is deſcribed, and the dignitie and worthineſſe of it expreſſed by a double expoſition; the firſt is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for it is not only a <hi>Church,</hi> but the Church of <hi>Chriſt: my Church.</hi> Secondly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and hence you haue the definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Church, as if he ſhould ſay, My Church is that building which I will build vpon this Rocke which thou haſt confeſſed: and therein you haue two propoſitions: Firſt, <hi>The Church is builded by Chriſt: I will build my Church.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Chriſt his Church is builded vpon a Rocke; and that not euerie Rocke, but vpon this Rocke: Vpon this Rocke I will build my Church.</hi> Laſtly, the inference or conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, becauſe it is the Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe he
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19941:6"/>builds it, becauſe hee builds it vpon that Rocke, <hi>therefore the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile againſt it.</hi> Heerein conſider two things: Firſt, what thoſe gates of hell are: ſecondly, how they preuaile not againſt that <hi>My Church,</hi> the Church of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> I ſhall ſhew you, that the Iewes were not onely the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> the <hi>Mount Moriah</hi> not properly the foundation: or the ſtones of the Iewes Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the ſtones of that building: I will ſhew you, that the Church is the company of Gods Elect and choſen; that <hi>Peter</hi> was not the head of it, but a ſtone of the building; that Chriſt is the ſure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and that whoſoeuer is builded on him, ſhall neuer be broken downe, no not by the gates of hell. Let me beg your attention in the name of Chriſt.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Peters prerogatiue, and therein firſt of the perſonall benefit which he receiued: which is the firſt thing.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THou art Peter.]</hi> The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, doth ſignifie a ſtone: the prerogatiue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which <hi>Peter</hi> had, is this, he is made a ſtone, <hi>non conuerſione naturae,</hi> not by conuerſion of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture into ſtone, <hi>ſed done gratiae,</hi> but hee is made a ſtone by the gift of grace. And he is made a ſtone two manner of waies; by his faith, and by his fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Heere is our Sauiour as good as his word; and performeth that promiſe which he made vnto
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19941:6"/>him,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.42.</note> when his brother <hi>Andrew</hi> firſt brought him vnto Chriſt. <hi>Thou art Simon, the ſonne of Iona, thou ſhalt bee called Cephas, which is by interpretation, a ſtone.</hi> And our Lord did reſerue the confirmation of his promiſe, till <hi>Peter</hi> had made this good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
               <p>The Church of God, which is the companie of thoſe whom God hath elected to life eternall, is often in the Scriptures reſembled to a materiall Temple, and in particular to the Temple of <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem;</hi> ſo that as that was called a houſe,
<note place="margin">Mat. 21.13.</note> 
                  <hi>the houſe of prayer;</hi> ſo is this called a houſe,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.2.</note> 
                  <hi>a ſpirituall houſe,</hi> for diſtinctions ſake. The materiall houſe was built of ſtones layed one vpon another; the ſpirituall houſe is likewiſe ſaid to bee <hi>builded,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.26. 1. Pet. 2.5.</note> builded of ſtones, not naturall ſtones, but <hi>liuing ſtones.</hi> The naturall ſtones of the materiall Temple, were ioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cimented one to another, that ſo the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding might riſe vp to perfection; and the ſpirituall ſtones <hi>are fitly framed together,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 2.21.</note> that the building may grow <hi>vnto an holy Temple of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, to make the ſimilitude more plaine, the materiall Temple had a ſtrong foundation, a <hi>Rocke,</hi> next to which were ſtones of great ſtrength, to ſupport the whole fabricke of the building, which ſtones might not improperly be called the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being indeed a ſecond foundation, moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for ſo great a pile, and afterwards it was raiſed with coſtly and curious ſtones,
<note place="margin">1 King. 6.7.</note> ſuch as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> made ready and brought thither; or ſuch as thoſe ſtones which the Diſciples did maruell at in the Temple,
<note place="margin">Mar. 13.1.</note> for the faireneſſe and the greatneſſe of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19941:7"/>them:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Antiq. lib.</hi> 15. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> which ſtones, as ſaith <hi>Ioſephus,</hi> were 25. cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits long, 8. cubits high, and 12. cubits broad. In like maner, this ſpirituall building is built on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> a moſt ſtrong and ſure foundation; (that is the firſt foundation:)
<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.16. Eph. 2.20.</note> 
                  <hi>the foundations are the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles;</hi> (they are the ſecond foundation:) and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe the members of the Church, as ſtones, are builded, according to that of the Apoſtle to the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>You are alſo builded together, for an habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God, through the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of this ſpirituall building S. <hi>Peter</hi> was a liuely ſtone. It is a name which no man knoweth, but he that hath it; hee doth eate of the Tree of life, and of the hidden <hi>Manna;</hi> he is a Citizen of Heauen, a fellow-Citizen of the Saints, and of the Familie of God: and to be layed in any place of this Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is an honour farre greater, then to bee exalted in the Palaces of Kings. The Queene of <hi>Sheba,</hi> when ſhe heard the wiſdome of <hi>Solomon,</hi> ſhee ſaid thus;
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> King. 10.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Happy are thy men, happy are theſe thy ſeruants, which ſtand continually before thee, and that heare thy wiſdome.</hi> Were theſe happy for hearing <hi>Solomons</hi> wiſdome? Were theſe happy for ſtanding before him? How much more happy are thoſe that ſtand builded in this ſpirituall Houſe, in which the Lord doth dwell, who heare his wiſdome, who are made wiſe vnto ſaluation, who receiue the ſecrets of the Goſpell, who are made the ſonnes of God, hearers and vnderſtanders of his wiſdome; and becauſe builded vpon that ſtrong and ſure foundation, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> is, therefore neuer to bee throwne downe? This happines is common to <hi>Peter,</hi> with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19941:7"/>euery true beleeuer; let vs therefore examine the matter further, that we may ſee what prerogatiue he might haue in this building, aboue other ſtones.</p>
               <p>I ſaid before, that he was made a ſtone by his faith, and by his function; by his faith he was made an Elect and precious ſtone; by his function hee was made a great ſtone, and a neceſſary foundation ſtone: by his faith hee was laid into the building; by his function he was was laid into the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the building: By the firſt, he had fellowſhip with the Saints; by the ſecond, hee had equality with the Apoſtles: vpon both theſe reſpects, <hi>dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus lapidem electum, pretioſum, neceſsarium, funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentalem.</hi> Wee ſay that he was a ſtone, a choice ſtone, a ſtone of great worth, meet for the building, and a ſtone of the Foundation.</p>
               <p>By his faith: It is not euery kinde of faith that maketh a ſtone, much leſſe ſuch a ſtone, a liuing ſtone, or if you will ſo haue it, a ſpirituall ſtone; for then were it poſſible that all men might bee ſtones of this building, becauſe it is not impoſſible that all men may haue one kind of Faith or other. There is a common faith which both the Elect and Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate haue, and there is a faith proper to the Elect of God, and this doth properly deſerue the name of faith: for to ſpeake Theologically, <hi>fides eſt electorum fides,</hi> faith is the faith of Gods Elect:
<note place="margin">Tit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1.2.</note> ſo ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that he is an Apoſtle, <hi>according to the faith of Gods Elect.</hi> The common faith is of three ſorts,
<note place="margin">Acts 8.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Hiſtoricall,</hi> whereby a man beleeueth the letter or Hiſtory of the Bible to be true: <hi>Temporary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iames 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a man doth not onely beleeue the Scripture, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19941:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:19941:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:19941:9"/>in particular, the Goſpell: but for ſome ſhort time doth make profeſſion, and perhaps doth bring forth ſome fruits, but he is not faithfull vnto death, and therefore hath nothing to doe with the Crowne of life.
<note place="margin">Reu. 2.10. Mat. 17.20. 1 Cor. 13.2.</note> Laſtly, the faith of <hi>Miracles,</hi> whereby the minde is carried with a vehement inſpiration of the Spirit, to doe ſignes and wonders in the Name of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Neither of theſe faiths doe make a man a ſtone in this ſpirituall and eternall building; and therefore though <hi>Simon</hi> had them all, they could not make him <hi>Peter,</hi> they could not make him a ſtone. The Diuels doe beleeue the Scriptures to be true;
<note place="margin">Iam. 2.19.</note> 
                  <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> the backſlider, and <hi>Iulian</hi> the reuolter, did for a time make profeſſion of them;
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.10.</note> and falſe prophets prophecie and caſt out Deuils, yea, and doe many wonderfull workes in the Name of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 7.22.</note> It is therefore worthy to be enquired what kind of faith St. <hi>Peters</hi> was: and becauſe we ſaid, that properly faith is the faith of the Elect, ſo we will call it; it was the iuſtifying or ſauing faith,
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.28.</note> which did lay hold on <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Sonne of the liuing God, who came to breake the Serpents head,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> and to deliuer vs from the Iawes of death; for <hi>Peter</hi> caught him in the armes of faith, when he confeſſed, ſaying, <hi>Thou art Chriſt the Sonne of the liuing God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let a man haue neuer ſo much knowledge, let him make neuer ſo great profeſſion, let him be able to remoue mountains, if he haue not this faith, he is as ſounding braſſe, or as a tinckling Cymball. This is the faith that maketh euery one that hath it a ſtone in the building; I will not ſay a ſtone ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19941:9"/>ſo bright-ſhining-glorious as <hi>Peter</hi> was (for euen among the foundation ſtones themſelues, there ſeemes to me to be ſome difference of gifts and graces in this life, and of glory in the life to come. <hi>The firſt foundation was Iaſper,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 21.19.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſecond Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyr, the third Calcedony, &amp;c.</hi> but a ſtone at leaſt, a true member of the Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the benefit whereof is,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.3.</note> that firſt he is waſhed from his naturall filthineſſe, and of a child of wrath is made the child of grace. Secondly, he is reconciled,
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> and is at peace with God through <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Thirdly, he is the child of God,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.17.</note> and an inheritor of the kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Laſtly, he attaineth all good gifts to bring him thereto; as ſauing knowledge, religious zeale, conſtant obedience, perſeuerance in grace, and what elſe you can thinke or ſpeake of; nay more then can come within the imagination of a naturall mans heart: for he dwelleth in God, and God dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in him, yea, God hath giuen him his Spirit whereby he knowes it.</p>
               <p>Let the proud and ambitious men of this world ſeeke after wealth and honour; let them <hi>Haman</hi>-like account the Kings fauour aboue all good things; let them haue ſumptuous Palaces, heapes of gold and ſiluer, and all pleaſures, as <hi>Salomon</hi> had; let them enioy theſe things with health, peace, and libertie: let them haue all the good things of the mind, body, &amp; fortune, which any naturall man (be he as acute as <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> or <hi>Plato</hi>) is able to wiſh for: this one gift of ſauing faith, poſſeſſed in the depth of pouerty, and worldly contempt, in the diſeaſed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and vlcerous skin of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and at the beſt,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19941:10"/>wandring vp and downe in Sheeps-shinnes, and Goats-skinnes, lodging in dennes and caues of the earth, with the ſeruants of the Lord, ſhall preſerue the poſſeſſors of it, in that great and terrible day of the Lords wrath, when the wicked ſhall vaniſh as ſmoake, and conſume away as the fat of Lambes. Let vs not therefore <hi>Midas</hi>-like ouer-value the things of this world, but beſtow our chiefeſt care how to attaine the ſauing faith: let vs not ſtudie how to bee grounded in wealth, but how to bee founded vpon <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Rocke: Let vs not emulate <hi>Semiramis</hi> in thoſe <hi>Babels</hi> that we build, but rather deuiſe how we our ſelues may be builded in this ſpirituall Houſe, of which <hi>Peter</hi> by ſauing faith was made a ſtone, and euery one that doth partake with <hi>Peter</hi> in the ſame faith, is likewiſe a ſtone, though not of ſo large a ſize, or ſo curiouſly carued; yet ſuch a ſtone as ſhall remaine in the building for eternitie,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 125.1.</note> like to Mount <hi>Sion</hi> that cannot be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
               <p>Now come we to his Function, the Office of his Apoſtleſhip, whereby he is made a ſtrong Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation ſtone, vpon whom other ſtones in the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding are fitly placed.
<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.21.</note> For <hi>Chriſt gaue ſome Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Euangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">12.</note> 
                  <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints for the worke of the Miniſtery, and for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the Body of Chriſt.</hi> Therefore the Apoſtles, the Prophets, the Euangeliſts, the Paſtors and Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the Church, are neceſſary ſtones for the building, that it may be raiſed. But the greateſt of all theſe are the Apoſtles, who, becauſe Apoſtles,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19941:10"/>are therefore Prophets, Euangeliſts, and Teachers.
<note place="margin">Mar. 10.2. <hi>Oſiand. Harmon Euang. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. Acts 1.26. Acts 9.15.</note> Yet no other can attaine the dignity of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhip, but the eleuen firſt choſen by our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the ſecond yeere of his Miniſtery, <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias,</hi> who ſucceeded in the place of <hi>Iudas</hi> the Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and <hi>Paul,</hi> that choſen and elect veſſell, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of the Gentiles laſt called. In reſpect of the Church, theſe are great Foundation ſtones, for they obtained commiſſion to teach all Nations, and to baptize them <hi>in the Name of the Father, of the Son,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> 
                  <hi>and of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 10.18.</note> Which Commiſſion of theirs they faithfully executed: for <hi>their ſound went into all the earth, and their words vnto the ends of the world.</hi> I need not tell you with what gifts and graces they were enriched, for the performance of ſo great a buſineſſe; ſurely they ſo preuailed, that by their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.47.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord added to the Church daily ſuch as ſhould be ſaued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe great ſtones vpon diuers reſpects are ſaid to lye in the Foundation of the building, for the ſupportation of other ſtones, leſſe in graces, and leſſe in office. Firſt, becauſe they were called to that office, not by the Miniſtery of man, but immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by God, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith that he is <hi>an Apoſtle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal 1.1.</note> 
                  <hi>not of men, neither by man.</hi> Secondly, becauſe they firſt of all had commiſſion to preach <hi>Chriſt</hi> crucified vnto the Gentlies, and to ioyne both Iewes and Gentiles into one people,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 11.10.</note> that ſo the <hi>roote of Ieſſe might ſtand for an Enſigne of the people, and the Gentiles might ſeeke vnto it.</hi> Thirdly, becauſe other great Officers of the Church, as Biſhops, Elders, and Deacons, were ordained by their Miniſtery,
<note place="margin">Acts 6.6.</note> and conſecrated
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19941:11"/>the hands of their Apoſtleſhip, but they themſelues were not ſo ordained, or ordered, but were cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen immediately by God, and receiued their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> his mouth. Laſtly, they ordained none to ſucceed them, in the fulneſſe of their office &amp; charge, that is to ſay, to go into all Nations, &amp; to preach the Goſpell vnto euery creature,
<note place="margin">Mar. 16.15.</note> which was their immediate commiſſion Apoſtolicall, but they ordained proper Paſtors vnto particular Churches, to whoſe care they recommended the Flocke of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in thoſe places where they themſelues had preached and preuailed, reſeruing vnto themſelues Apoſtolick dignity, euen to ouerſee the Biſhops and Elders of the Church. And hence it is that St. <hi>Paul</hi> duiſeth <hi>Timothy</hi> &amp; <hi>Titus,</hi> how to behaue themſelues in their function: and that St. <hi>Peter</hi> taketh vpon him to inſtruct the Elders of the Church, and that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> counſelleth, reprooueth, and commendeth the Angels or Biſhops of the ſeuen Churches of <hi>Aſia.</hi> Theſe things being branches of the Apoſtolicke authoritie, it was no ſmall matter that our Sauiour performed vnto <hi>Peter</hi> vpon his confeſſion, ſaying, <hi>Thou art Peter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Note here what excellent Miniſters God hath raiſed vp in his Church for the ſauing of the ſoules of his Elect! By theſe the excellency of Chriſtian Religion is much commended: they are Apoſtles, Prophets, Euangeliſts, Paſtours and Teachers. If the <hi>Indian</hi> Schooles grew in eſtimation, becauſe of the Gymnoſophiſts, and the <hi>Perſian</hi> wiſedome by the Soothſayers, and the <hi>Egyptian</hi> learning by the Sorcerers, how much more ſhall our Religion bee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19941:11"/>aduanced, by the worthineſſe of the Miniſters, and their high calling in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus?</hi> This ſhould alſo teach men, to haue a reuerend regard vnto the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Word: for they are not onely ſtones in the building, if they be faithfull, but neceſſary workemen, for the edifying of Gods Church, and in reſpect of their Office cloſely laid vpon the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles for the building of <hi>Chriſt</hi> his Body, and therefore, <hi>Let a man ſo account of vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.1.</note> 
                  <hi>as of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the Myſteries of God.</hi> Hitherto we haue ſpoken of <hi>Peters</hi> perſonall bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit: now come we vnto that thing whereunto it hath relation, and that is the Church, vnto which it hath reference, as a ſtone to the building.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vpon this Rocke will I build my Church.]</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Secondly, of the Church, and therein, firſt, that it is a Church, and more then that, the Church of Chriſt, <hi>my Church.</hi>
                  </note> The Elect and choſen of God, ſaith the Text, are a Church, and more then that, <hi>my Church,</hi> the Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is deriued from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which ſignifieth to call out or ſummon: ſo that when you talke of the Church, it is as if you ſhould ſay a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of men called out or ſummoned. The <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> were wont to call the Company of Citizens, called out or ſummoned by the voyce of the Crier to heare the ſentence of the Senate <hi>Eccleſiam.</hi> And by the Etymologie of this word, the condition of Gods elect &amp; choſen, is fitly expreſſed; for they are called out of the generality of men, by the Word of God, to know God, and to worſhip and ſerue him: and this their Calling, becauſe they obey it, wee call an effectuall Vocation. Theſe ſo effectually called, are in the Scriptures ſet forth to bee a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19941:12"/>
                  <hi>people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.8. Epheſ. 2.19. <hi>Clem. Alexand. Strom. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Ambroſ. in Ephe. cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Bernar. in Cant. Str.</hi> 78.</note> 
                  <hi>the houſhold of God,</hi> whom <hi>Clemens Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinus</hi> calleth the company of the Elect. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, a people whom God hath vouchſafed to adopt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelfe. Bernard, the company of the elected, which company was predeſtinated before the world began.</hi> To ſpeake expreſly of this <hi>Church,</hi> it is gathered out of all Sexes, Orders, Nations, and Times, and it is therefore called the <hi>Catholicke or Vniuerſall Church.</hi> Secondly, whereas ſome of the members of this <hi>Catholicke</hi> Church, are taken out of the vale of teares, and conueighed into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome; in reſpect of them the <hi>Church is triumphant:</hi> and whereas ſome are left in this Forreſt of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> to wreſtle with the Diuell, the World, and the Fleſh; in reſpect of them, the <hi>Church is Militant.</hi> Laſtly, in reſpect of the outward practice of Religion, the <hi>Church is Viſible,</hi> and in reſpect of the faith of the beleeuers, it is <hi>inuiſible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The condition therefore of the Church in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and of euery member in particular, is to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out: but they are not all called out at one age, at one time, or vpon one occaſion. That great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Vineyard, hired ſome of his labourers very early in the morning, ſome at the third houre, ſome at the ſixt, ſome at the ninth, and ſome at the eleuenth houre. <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> was ſanctified from his mothers wombe; <hi>Timothie</hi> was called in his youth: <hi>Paul</hi> a young man; and the Thiefe vpon the Croſſe at the laſt gaſpe. Againe, it is not one kinde of meanes that doth preuaile to win all thoſe that are called to the faith, or (if you will haue it ſo) not the ſame manner or method of preaching.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19941:12"/>
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was inſnared by the eloquence of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe:</hi> and the great diſputer at the <hi>Nicene Councell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. Confeſſ. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f. Eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſt. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> was caught by the words of a plaine man. GOD hath ſanctified the eloquent tongue of the learned man to preuaile on ſome; and the humble ſpeech of the vnlearned to preuaile on others: for he that doth ordinarily call men by his Word, is, if it pleaſe him, able to conuert the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without his Word. Let no man ceaſe to hope wel of his brother, thogh for the preſent hee ſee noe uident tokens of his obedience: God hath a time for him: <hi>ſeriùs ociùs Sors exitura,</hi> firſt or laſt it may fall to his lot: the Lord of the Harueſt may, if it pleaſe him, ſend him into the vineyard, though at the eleuenth houre. <hi>O ter<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> quater<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> beati,</hi> thrice happy all thoſe whom the Lord doth call effectually to his ſeruice!</p>
               <p>Againe, let vs not bee abſent when God doth call; for if we heare not, how ſhall we obey? Had the fiue wiſe Virgins beene out of the way when the Bridegroome did come, how had they beene admitted into the wedding Chamber?
<note place="margin">Mat. 25. Luc. 19.</note> Had <hi>Zachae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> not ſtood in the way, how had Chriſt called him from the tree? Strange it is to ſee the practice of the world; we account him ſottiſh, or rather mad, who will abſent himſelfe when a worldly prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be gotten; <hi>per ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, per ſaxa, per ignes,</hi> we ride and runne, when we may be heard for our profit: yet when the King of Heauen calleth vs by his Word and Sacraments, we ſticke not to goe about our worldly buſineſſes, nay, our pleaſures and delights, as Playes, Tau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, and worſe things then theſe two! <hi>O miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ania, ciues?</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:19941:13"/>Shall we be ſo ſtudious of theſe things, and ſhall we not attend for our eternall profit? Laſtly, let vs not bring itching eares into Gods Houſe, but humble and obedient hearts; and becauſe the Miniſters of the Word doe ſummon vs on Gods behalfe, let not our owne delights and pleaſures, let not the wicked worlds ſinnes and vanities, reteine our hearts in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:</hi> for Gods Family is <hi>Eccleſia,</hi> a company cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out.</p>
               <p>This Church ſo ſelected,
<note place="margin">Of the ſecond expoſition, &amp; therein of the firſt propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>viz</hi> the Church is buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Chriſt. <hi>I will build my Church.</hi> 1 Cor. 3.9. Exod. 36.1.</note> ſo called out, is buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or rather called out that it may be builded; for it is <hi>Gods building.</hi> When GOD would haue his Tabernacle in the wilderneſſe, he ſanctified <hi>Beza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leel</hi> and <hi>Aholiab</hi> for the worke: <hi>and into many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers he put wiſdome and vnderſtanding, to know how to worke all manner of worke, for the ſeruice of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie, according to all that the Lord had comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi> The ſumptuous Temple of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 6.7.</note> 
                  <hi>was of ſtone made ready, before it was brought thither, ſo that there was neither hammer, nor axe, nor any toole of yron heard in the Houſe while it was in building.</hi> A further preparation for the building of the ſpirituall Houſe, was heereby fitly ſhaddowed: <hi>viz. Chriſt,</hi> who is to build his <hi>Church,</hi> doth firſt prepare the ſtones: ſecondly, hee ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth certaine wiſe workmen to lay them into the pile: thirdly, he directeth them how to build: and laſtly, by this meanes the ſtones are placed. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this to be the order of the building.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the preparation of the ſtones is meerely Gods worke, who himſelfe ſorteth and chooſeth out ſuch as he will lay into the Temple, <hi>de diuinae
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19941:13"/>gratiae largitate,</hi> of the bounty of his diuine grace, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. Euchirid. cap.</hi> 98. Eph. 1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>For he hath choſen vs in him before the foundation of the world, that we ſhould be holy, and without blame before him in loue.</hi> By this meanes we come to be ſtones for the worke, <hi>per miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam gratuitam,</hi> by the free mercie of God; others being caſt by, <hi>per iudicium debitum,</hi> by the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous iudgement of God; that ſo in this reſpect wee might attribute nothing to our ſelues, or glory in any thing that we can doe, but according to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall counſell, <hi>He that glorieth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.17.</note> 
                  <hi>let him glory in the Lord.</hi> Secondly, the Miniſters of the Word doe worke vpon theſe choice ſtones, to lay them into the pile, and for this cauſe are called <hi>builders.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> affirmeth himſelfe to be <hi>a wiſe Maſter-builder.</hi> And they are ſanctified, ſeparated,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.10.</note> or put apart from men, for this worke: as the Apoſtle ſaith that he is <hi>ſeparated vnto the Goſpell of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.1.</note> Like as in the building of that great <hi>Epheſian</hi> Temple, one of the worlds ſeuen wonders, erected by all <hi>Aſia,</hi> in 220. yeeres, as <hi>Plinie</hi> reporteth,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 36. <hi>Cap.</hi> 14.</note> the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders layed a ſure foundation of Coles trodden and rammed hard together, and fleeces of Wooll ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>impoſed, to keepe it from ſinking and from earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes: ſo the builders whom God doth call, and ſanctifie to that office, doe in this ſpirituall Houſe vſe all good meanes to preſerue their worke, that nothing may bee able to demoliſh it. Thirdly, they haue receiued rule and direction: for GOD who will haue his Church to be builded, doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the workmen how to doe it: and therfore they worke according as they haue receiued order from
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19941:14"/>him. Now God directeth the builders two man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wayes, ordinarily or extraordinarily. Our ordinary direction is the written Word, which teacheth the true and right faith, according to which we muſt build.
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Let vs propheſie according to the proportion of faith.</hi> It is therefore requiſite, that the Workmen be learned in the Scriptures, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare ſpirituall things with ſpirituall things; to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne which is the faith, which is not the faith; which thing is to be done by the Scriptures: for, <hi>Sacra ſcriptura haereticoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fraudes et furta conuincit:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertullian.</note> the bleſſed Scripture reproueth the ſleights and thefts of Hereticks: thence therefore they muſt ordinarily fetch their directions, and be inſtructed how to build;
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.17.</note> for they will make the man of God abſolute. Extraordinarily, the builders are direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſometimes immediately by God himſelfe, and by his holy Angels, as the ancient Fathers from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> to <hi>Moſes:</hi> ſometimes by viſions and reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as the Prophets from <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Chriſt:</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by the immediate inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt, as the Apoſtles. Which extraordinarie meanes beeing now moſt rare, the direction on which the builders muſt looke, is the written Word of God, together with the inward aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt. Will you know then how to make experience whether any builder be inwardly guided by the Spirit of God? Heare then how one of the learned Fathers concludes the point:
<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>and. Spirit.</note> There bee many (ſaith he) who doe bragge that they haue the Holy Ghoſt: for they that ſpeake of their owne, doe falſly giue out that they haue him. For as Chriſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19941:14"/>did deny that he ſpake of himſelfe, when hee ſpake out of the Law and the Prophets: euen ſo now, if any thing ſaue the Goſpell be thruſt vpon vs, vnder the name of the Holy Ghoſt, we muſt not beleeue it. For as Chriſt is the fulfilling of the Law, and of the Prophets, euen ſo is the Holy Ghoſt the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Goſpell. Laſtly, by theſe good meanes, this doth come to paſſe, that the ſtones are well placed in the Walles of this ſpirituall houſe: for the labourers in Gods Harueſt,
<note place="margin">Mat. 9.37.</note> whom he directeth by his Word and Spirit, doe ſtrongly proue, and make appeare by the authority of the Word of GOD, that <hi>God ſo loued the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>that he gaue his onely begotten Sonne; that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him, ſhould not periſh, but haue euerlaſting life.</hi> This labour of theirs, with the aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, bringeth this to paſſe; that firſt their minds are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened, to ſee their owne miſery in and by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Secondly, their willes are inflamed to ſeeke reconciliation with God in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And it is admirable to ſee how God hath bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the labours of his ſeruants, to lay thoſe liuing ſtones into the walles of this ſpirituall Houſe, who are well placed there by faith and baptiſme. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> hauing fully opened the ſtate of the queſtion, and proued mightily Chriſt to be the Redeemer,
<note place="margin">Act. 2.41.</note> at one Sermon conuerted about 3000. ſoules, who were alſo baptized. How graciouſly were theſe ſtones layed in and placed? <hi>Auguſtine</hi> confeſſeth of himſelfe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Confeſ. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> that he heard <hi>Ambroſe</hi> but for his elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence ſake; <hi>et dum cor aperirem ad decipiendum quam diſertè diceret, pariter intrabat &amp; quam verè di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret:</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:19941:15"/>By this meanes the Lord caught him; for while he conceiued how learnedly hee diſcourſed, he perceiued alſo how truly hee ſpake: both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts entred together, as heate and light which cannot bee ſeparated. Admirably was this ſtone layed in and placed. By <hi>Caecilius,</hi> a Miniſter of Chriſt, was <hi>Cyprian</hi> that bleſſed Martyr conuerted to the faith:
<note place="margin">Nazian. laudib. Cyprian.</note> He was both rich and Noble, as <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zienzene</hi> reporteth of him: hee was of great note for his learning and eloquence,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lactant. inſtit. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh. Trithem. de ſcript. Cypr. Pont. Diacon. de vita Cypr.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>Hierom</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantius</hi> ſay. And therefore, conſidering his ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, as a rich and noble man, hee might haue ſcorned to haue heard; and as a learned and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent man, diſdained to haue beene taught by ſo meane a Miniſter as <hi>Caecilius</hi> was: but the LORD would haue him to be layed into the building by his Miniſtery, and therefore he was not onely won to the faith, but euen at the firſt, to ſhew that hee would practiſe what he had learned, he ſold all his ſubſtance, and beſtowed it vpon the poore: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by (as <hi>Pontius Diaconus</hi> well concludeth) <hi>paene antè coepit perfectus eſſe quam diſceret:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De vita Cypr.</note> he began to bee a perfect man in his religion, almoſt before hee had learned the rules of it. Was not this a bleſſed ſtone, worke-man-like layed in and placed?</p>
               <p>Wonder heere at the vndeſerued loue of GOD toward his redeemed ones?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiph. ad Phyſiol. cap.</hi> 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Diuina opera incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſibilia ſunt in hominibus, &amp; mirabilia in excelſis, &amp; ſuper mel &amp; fanum, &amp; ſuper creata omnia dulciora.</hi> His workes are incomprehenſible to men: for who can giue a reaſon of the choiſe of theſe liuing ſtones? His workes are admirable in heauen; euen
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19941:15"/>the Angels themſelues haue cauſe to admire the goodneſſe of God toward his people. His workes are ſweeter then the honey, the honey Combe, or any thing created: Behold how good it is vnto his people, not to bee choiſe ſtones onely, but to haue their Election made ſure vnto them, and by faith and baptiſme, through the miniſterie of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full workmen, directed by his Word and Spirit, to be layed into the building. All this were yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if the houſe ſtood but vpon ſandy ground; and therefore to take away all doubts, our Sauiour telleth vs whereupon his Church is built: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>vpon this Rocke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vpon this Rocke.]</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Secondly, of the ſecond propoſition, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Church is built vpon Chriſt the Rocke. <hi>Rainolds Conf. Hart. c.</hi> 2. <hi>diuiſ</hi> 1. <hi>Lex. Graec. ad ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cri appar. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct. reg. b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>lior. Tom.</hi> 6. <hi>Thomaſ. voce pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra. Illyr. voce petra.</hi>
                  </note> I will not much contend with our Aduerſaries concerning words: onely this I affirme, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> doth alwayes ſignifie a ſtone, neuer a rocke: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> doth moſt vſually ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a rocke, <hi>grandem aliquam rupem, &amp; viuum la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidem,</hi> though ſometimes it be likewiſe taken for a ſtone. In this place it cannot ſignifie a ſtone, but a rocke; for our Sauiour is ſpeaking of the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his great building, the Church; vpon which foundation he would lay many <hi>Peters,</hi> many ſtones. This you ſhall ſee further, by the metaphoricall acceptions of the word; for ſometimes <hi>petra</hi> is a firme place, by way of oppoſition to ſandy or mud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ground:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee brought me vp alſo out of an horrible pit, out of the mirie clay, and ſet my feete vpon a rocke, and ſtabliſhed my goings.</hi> Sometimes it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth a place fortified and inexpugnable, like vnto a Caſtle builded vpon a high craggy Rocke, againſt which the power of the Enemie cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19941:16"/>
                  <hi>Leaue the Cities,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hier. 48.28. Pſal. 18.2. Pſal. 31.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and dwell in the Rocke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, God is ſaid to be our Rocke, <hi>The Lord is my Rocke, Be thou my ſtrong Rocke, for an houſe of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to ſaue me.</hi> This is the metaphor vſed in this place; for our Sauiour telleth <hi>Peter,</hi> who is the Rock of his Church, that firm place vpon which his Church ſtandeth, that inexpugnable high Rocke, vpon which it is ſituated; namely, himſelfe whom <hi>Peter</hi> had confeſſed, when he ſaid, <hi>Thou art Chriſt the Sonne of the liuing God.</hi> In this meaning haue the Fathers with great iudgement interpreted this place.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. de verb. dom. Ser.</hi> 13. <hi>Greg. Nyſſen. in teſtim. de Trinn. Cont. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeos. Cyryl. de Trinit. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Chryſoſt. in Mat. Hom.</hi> 55. <hi>Amb. in Epiſt. ad Epheſ. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Hill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r de Trint. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6. <hi>Bed. in</hi> 1 <hi>Cor: cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>This Rocke which thou haſt confeſsed</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine) vpon this Rocke which thou haſt knowne, (ſaying, Thou art Chriſt the Sonne of the liuing God) will I build my Church: I will build thee vpon me, not me vpon thee. For men intending to build vpon men, ſaid, I hold of Paul, I of Apollos, I of Cephas, (that is, Peter) and others who would not be builded vpon Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but vpon the Rocke, ſaid, I hold of Chriſt. For the Rocke was Chriſt, vpon which foundation, Peter himſelfe was builded, ſith no man can lay any other foundation, beſide that which is laid, which is Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And in this ſame ſenſe, haue <hi>Gregory Nyſsen, Cyril, Chryſoſtome, Ambroſe, Hillarie, Venerable Bede,</hi> and many other ancient Fathers, and learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, vnderſtood this place otherwiſe then the <hi>Theologians</hi> of the <hi>Ieſuiticall</hi> Order, the pillars of the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> would haue it.</p>
               <p>And Chriſt is the Rocke of his Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is the Redeemer of his Church. For by <hi>Adams</hi> fall all mankind being in the loynes of <hi>Adam, tanquam in radice,</hi> as it were in the roote
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19941:16"/>of mans nature, as the Fathers ſpeake) both <hi>Adam</hi> and all his poſterity were caſt into the mire: but the Rocke was promiſed, when the promiſe of the womans bleſſed ſeed,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> 
                  <hi>to breake the Serpents head was made:</hi> which promiſe, when <hi>Adam</hi> apprehended by faith, he was then built vpon the Rocke, and not all mankinde which had fallen in and by him, though it were then in his loynes, but onely the elected members of the Church, who by the ſame faith ſhould apprehend the ſame ſauing promiſe which <hi>Adam</hi> did. The Rocke of the Church there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, is the <hi>Redeemer;</hi> for the Church hath no other Rocke to be builded on. Hence it muſt neceſſarily follow, that in what reſpect he is the Redeemer of the Church, in the ſame ſenſe is he the Rocke on which it is builded: but he is the Redeemer of the Church, <hi>qua</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; therefore as he is both God and Man, hee is that Rocke on which the Church is built. And I ſay that he is the Rocke, <hi>qua</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe that both natures are vndi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidedly neceſſary to the redemption of mankinde. How ſhould a ſatisfaction be made proportionable to our debt, but by the diuine Nature? How ſhould a cure be found to an infinite euill, but by an infinit good? how ſhould death be vanquiſhed, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinne, and the infiniteneſſe of the diuine Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice be ſuſtained, but by the diuine Nature? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, who can giue ſatisfaction to the Iuſtice of God according to the Law, by ſuffering ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by obeying perfectly, but onely man made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law? who could ſuffer death, <hi>being made a curſe, that ſo in all things he might be made like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19941:17"/>his brethren, that he might be a mercifull, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full high Prieſt, in things pertaining to God, to make reconciliation for the ſinnes of the people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſeb. 2.17.</note> but onely man? See the neceſſitie of the humane Nature! thus it behoued the Redeemer, the Rocke, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming Rocke to be both God and man.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ludouic. Gran. ducis peccat. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>part.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Sum quidemſummo iure tibi obſtrictus Domine mi, eo quod me liberaſti ab inferno, me<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tibi reconciliaſti: multa vero maiora tibi debeo propter modu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſum quo me li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beraſti, quam propter ipſam libertatem, in quam me aſseruiſti.</hi> Highly am I bound vnto God, that hee hath vouchſafed to redeeme me from Hell, and to reconcile me to himſelfe; but in afarre greater band am I bound for the manner of my Redemption, then for that libertie into which hee hath brought me.</p>
               <p>Set before your eyes the great myſtery of your Redemption, looke vpon the manner after which it was done, and if it was not grieuous to the Sonne of God, to aſſume vnto himſelfe the humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; nay, the ſinnes of men; nay, the penalty due by the Law to ſinners, that he might be the Redeemer of his <hi>Church:</hi> you that profeſſe your ſelues to be members of that ſaued Family, let it not bee grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous vnto you, to come forth of the <hi>Sodom</hi> of this worlds ſinnes and vices, with which <hi>Chriſt</hi> will haue no peace, and a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> will haue no agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (<hi>viz.</hi> your pride, your luſts, your intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, and what things elſe are forbidden by the Law of God,) that like as the Word of God doth acquaint you with the myſtery of your Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Spirit of God may ſeale vnto your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19941:17"/>the day of your Redemption. Till this bee ſealed, though you haue the world at will, though you be planted as high as the Cedars of <hi>Libanus,</hi> in wealth and honours, though you come into no miſ-fortunes like other men, though there bee no leading into captiuitie, no complaining in your ſtreets, I will not therefore magnifie your happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Why? your conſciences doe tremble when you thinke of death, Sinne raigneth in your mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall bodies, and the ſentence of the Law threatneth a fearefull iudgement. I note not here how neere ſuch a one is to the deſperation of <hi>Iudas Iſcariot:</hi> but what can he hope for, who doeth willingly, either contemne or neglect ſo great ſaluation? It is a great and a fearefull ſinne to commit adultery or mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it is a greater ſin to commit periurie or idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; moſt vncleane are ſuch perſons, and the doores of Heauen are cloſe ſhut againſt them, both in this world, and in the world to come,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.17.</note> without great and vnfained repentance: but to <hi>diſobey the Goſpell of God,</hi> to caſt aſide the Redeemer, that ſure Rocke, vpon which, whoſoeuer is not built, ſhall ſurely bee blowne downe; oh, how great is that ſinne? how wide doth Hell gape for ſuch a one? Conſider this, ye <hi>Gadarens,</hi> who preferre your Swine before <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (for ſo doth euery one, who will not be a new creature in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> for the loue of any kind of ſinne) and if yee will not hearken and be wiſe, but ſtill goe on to faſhion your ſelues like vnto this world; yet that you may not be ignorant of your owne miſerable condition, behold the happineſſe of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and therefore the bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19941:18"/>of euery member of the ſame. It is built, it is firmely builded, it is builded vpon a Rocke, a redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Rocke, the Rocke <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neuer bee ouerthrowne by all the aduerſe power.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The gates of Hell ſhall not preuale againſt it.]</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, and firſt what thoſe gates of Hell are. <hi>Noua gloſſa in Mat.</hi> 16.18.</note> Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this reaſon that the gates of Cities are moſt ſtrongly fortified, and moſt firmely barred and bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by gates you may vnderſtand, <hi>omne robur, &amp; omne munimentum,</hi> all power and all fortification; and by Hell, <hi>omnem vim contrariam, &amp; Satanicam, omnem host is impetum,</hi> the Diuell himſelfe, and all his angels, all the power that they haue, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked world,
<note place="margin">Illyric. voce porta.</note> all tyrants and ſeducers, which are the Diuels inſtruments. For to make the matter more plaine in the words of a learned man, the ſtate of the faithfull and choſen of God, in this preſent life, is as it were a <hi>Warfare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.4.</note> whereof the <hi>Church</hi> is called <hi>Militant.</hi> The aduerſaries and enemies, whom we muſt fight againſt, our Sauiour ſpeaketh of them as of a ſtrong kingdome,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 2 Cor. 10.4.</note> which he calleth <hi>Hell,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it warreth all for <hi>Hell, and the Diuell is the prince</hi> of it. The gates of Hell therefore doe ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie <hi>the holds,</hi> the fortreſſes and munitions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the powers of Hell doe fight againſt vs, and aſſault vs, that is, euen all whatſoeuer the Diuell can doe by force or fraud; all the which is meant by the name of gates, becauſe the gates of forts are wont to haue the beſt munition,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiphan. lib.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>r. Aug. de S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>b. 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</note> and to be fenced moſt ſtrongly. So that the gates of Hell are not onely <hi>Hereſies</hi> (though Hereſies are of them, as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and <hi>Auſtin</hi> note) but alſo perſecutions,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19941:18"/>and ſpecially ſinnes; in a word, all euils, ſweet or ſowre, faire or foule,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Orig. in Mat. tract.</hi> 1. <hi>Chryſoſt. cont. gent. quod Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus eſt Deus. Greg. in</hi> 5. <hi>Pſal. poenitent. Theophil. in Mat.</hi> 16. <hi>Hier. &amp; Raban. Com. in Mat.</hi> 16. <hi>Raynold. Confer. cap.</hi> 7. <hi>diuiſ.</hi> 8. <hi>Cypr. ad Donat. Epiſt.</hi> 2.</note> that ſeeke to ſubdue vs to euerlaſting death, as <hi>Origen, Chryſoſtome, Gregory, Theophilact,</hi> and others well obſerue.</p>
               <p>Let me now ſay vnto you, as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaid to a friend of his: Suppoſe thy ſelfe to bee carried to the top of ſome high hill, view the world beneath thee, doe not touch the earth, looke round about thee, and behold how tempeſtuous the world is, <hi>iam ſaeculi &amp; ipſe miſereberis, tui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> admonitus, &amp; plus in Deum gratus, maio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e laetitia quod enaſeris gratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laberis:</hi> certainely, thou wilt pitty the world, thou wilt be admoniſhed of thine owne condition, and being more thankfull vnto God, wilt reioyce ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly, that thou haſt eſcaped ſuch a place. For ſhall I tell you? Ye ſhall ſee wonders in the world; and I will report that vnto you, which, if yee haue the Spirit of God in you, ſhall prick your conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. In the Booke of <hi>Iudges,</hi> it is reported as an argument of <hi>Samſons</hi> great ſtrength,
<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.3.</note> that he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the gates of <hi>Gaza</hi> vpon his ſhoulders: an act almoſt as great as what the Poets can report of <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las.</hi> But ſee, not the weake gates of <hi>Gaza,</hi> but the ſtrong gates of Hell, not vpon the ſhoulders and backs of men and women only, but (that which you may admire) ſet vpon their heads, layed out by their cheekes, worne vpon their hand-wreſts, hung at their eares. <hi>O tempora, ô mores!</hi> elſe what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth this monſtrous pride of apparell, of tyres, of bracelets, of Iewels, ouerflowing our nation like a generall deluge? You put the gates of Hell into your purſes, by taking of bribes, vſurie money, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill gettings: you ſet them at your tables in the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19941:19"/>perſons of Hereticks and ſeducers: you lodge them in your beds by vnlawfull luſts: you let them in at your eares, when you liſten to vngodlines: you looke vpon them with your eyes, when you ſee in your houſes that accurſed thing which you ought to reſtore: you lay them vp in your hearts, when you deuiſe vaine things. Certainely, for many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, this Citie may be called an holy Citie: for heere the Word of GOD is moſt plentifully preached: heere are good Lawes; and (for ought I know) good Magiſtrates; and (I make no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion) many thouſands of honeſt and obedient hearts. Yet the cauſe being the ſame, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint muſt needs be the ſame alſo;
<note place="margin">Iſai. 1.21.</note> 
                  <hi>How is the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Citie become an Harlot?</hi> The abuſe of all good things within this place is wonderfull, and doth ring <hi>Migremus hine, in the eares of euery good man,</hi> who might vtterly faint and bee diſcouraged, did he not hope verily to ſee the goodnes of the Lord in the Land of the liuing. I ſay, the wickedneſſe of the place, might vtterly diſmay, deceiue and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the children of GOD themſelues, had not Chriſt ſo builded them vpon himſelfe, that the gates of hell <hi>ſhall not preuaile</hi> againſt them.</p>
               <p>The words are,
<note place="margin">Secondly, how the gates of Hell preuaile not againſt the Church of Chriſt. Pſal. 139.1.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; Hee doth not ſay, they ſhall not aſſaile it, but they ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt it. <hi>Many a time haue they afflicted me from my youth, may Iſrael now ſay: Many a time haue they afflicted me from my youth: yet they haue not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed againſt me.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2.</note> 
                  <hi>The plowers plowed vpon my backe, they made long forrowes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord is righteous, he hath out aſunder the cords of the wicked.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4.</note> Theſe gates of hell doe aſſaile the Church generally, and euery
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19941:19"/>particular member of the ſame, both externally by ſlanders and perſecutions, and internally, by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, temptations, and inward ſuggeſtions; ſo that to ſpeake properly; in all places, and at all times, the gates of hell come about them like Bees: for the Diuell, the Prince of Hell, <hi>our Aduerſarie,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8.</note> as a roring Lyon, walketh about, ſeeking whom he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure.</hi> They haue likewiſe preuailed thus farre, that they haue tempted them ſometimes by great and grieuous loſſes, of their goods, names and bodies; but that which the Poets feigne of <hi>Siſyphus,</hi> wee may truly affirme of them; their labour is loſt, and the miſchieues which they haue deuiſed, haue euer returned vpon themſelues. They were neuer able to mooue the Church, or any true beleeuer, from that Rocke. Shall I ſay more? The impious at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of the gates of Hell, haue beene as well to the publike weale of the Church,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> as to the priuate good of her particular members. For, <hi>all things worke together for good to them that loue God, to them who are the called according to his purpoſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vpon this reſolution the people of God haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly indured, couragiouſly contemning all the gates of hell, battering the Walles of the <hi>Church,</hi> like that great Ram, with which the <hi>Romane</hi> Armie did day and night beate the Walles of <hi>Hieruſalem. Troy</hi> was beſieged tenne yeeres, in the end it was taken by policie. <hi>Numantia</hi> was beſieged fourteene yeeres, and then conquered by famine. <hi>Tyrus,</hi> a Citie walled with the Sea, in ſeuen moneths was ouercome by aſſault. But the Church of GOD, ſtraitly begirt, not by <hi>Agamemnon</hi> and <hi>Menelaus,</hi> not by <hi>Scipio Africanus,</hi> or <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:19941:20"/>not for tenne or foureteene yeeres, but from the beginning of the world, and expecting to be ſo dealt withal vnto the worlds end, by the Deuil and all his power, ſhall neuer, either by policie or force, be ruined:
<note place="margin">Iſa. 49.16.</note> for Chriſt is the Rocke and Head of his Church, and hath the walls of it euer in his ſight. This which is true of the Church in generall, is as true of euery particular member: for all the true members thereof are elected to life eternall, and builded vpon Chriſt the Rocke. And therfore the Church,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambr. in Luc.</hi> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 3.</note> as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, may rightly be defined to be <hi>Mater vinentium, quam aedificauit Deus in ipſo ſummo angulari lapide Chriſto:</hi> the mother of thoſe whom GOD hath preordained to life eternall, which he hath built vpon Chriſt the chiefe corner ſtone: they may therefore be aſſaulted, but neuer vanquiſhed; and if you will know how, heare a few examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> was fiercely aſſaulted by the gates of Hell, euen the wealth and honours of <hi>Egypt.</hi> I will not ſay what a ſtrong temptation it is. When the Deuill goeth about to winne vs by proſperitie, he doth then creepe in at our mouthes, that hee may poſſeſſe our heart: like the Fiſh called <hi>Langa,</hi> who flattereth the Whale, and creepeth in at his belly, that he may eate his heart. He who had experience of this temptation, did fore-warne and fore-arme the people of Iſrael,
<note place="margin">Deut. 8.12.</note> ſaying, <hi>Leſt when thou haſt eaten and art full, and haſt built goodly houſes, and dwelt therein;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">13.</note> 
                  <hi>And when thy heards and thy flocks multiply, and thy ſiluer and thy gold is multiplied,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">14.</note> 
                  <hi>and all that thou haſt is multiplyed: Then thine heart be lifted vp, and thou forget the Lord thy God, which brought thee
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19941:20"/>out of the land of Egypt, &amp;c.</hi> For man in proſperity is like vnto the Mule, who hauing ſuckt his fill of his Dams milke, caſteth vp his heeles, and kicketh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly. But the gates of Hell could not preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him;
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.24.</note> 
                  <hi>He refuſed to be called the ſonne of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Daughter, chooſing rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, then to enioy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon:
<note place="margin">25.</note> Eſteeming the reproach of Chriſt greater riches then the treaſures in Egypt;
<note place="margin">26.</note> for hee had reſpect vnto the recompence of the reward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iob</hi> was ſtrongly aſſaulted by the gates of Hell, he was bereaued of all his ſubſtance; his children were ſlaine with the fall of their eldeſt brothers houſe; and his owne body was ſmitten with ſore biles,
<note place="margin">Iob. 1, &amp; 2.</note> from the ſole of his foote vnto the Crowne of his head. Deare vnto a man are his goods and ſeruants; dearer are his children, the fruit of his owne body; but moſt deare vnto a man is his own fleſh. Oh, how great was this temptation! neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe it preuailed not, for he had ſet vp his reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, <hi>Though he ſlay me, yet will I truſt in him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 13.15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego</hi> were ſtrongly beſieged by the gates of Hell, for they muſt either ſall downe &amp; worſhip the golden Image that <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi> the King had ſet vp, or the ſame ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e be caſt into the middeſt of a burning fiery fornace. What will not a man giue for his life? Many men haue beene conſtant in Religion, they haue loſt their goods, their places, their honours, yet when their liues haue come in queſtion, they haue fallen away like rotten corne out of the Reapers hand. And no maruell if thoſe who were not built vpon the Rocke, did fall away, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>eing that euen
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19941:21"/>the Apoſtles themſelues in time of perſecution, when they thought their liues would come in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.56.</note> and our Sauiour was apprehended, <hi>forſooke him and fled.</hi> But the gates of Hell could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt them,
<note place="margin">Dan. 3.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Our God whom we ſerue, is able to deliuer vs out of the fiery furnace, and hee will deliuer vs out of thy hand, O King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Behold the good eſtate of euery true member of the Church of <hi>Chriſt!</hi> It is neither the proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the wicked world, nor all the worldly miſeries and calamities which may be thought vpon, no nor death it ſelfe that ſhal be able to caſt them from the Rocke. I doe not ſay that all true beleeuers are equall in graces to theſe that I haue named; for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth God ſuffer them all to be tempted in equall meaſure; but I affirme all of them to haue the ſame grace to the ſame purpoſe, the ſauing of their ſoules. And hence it is that a regenerate mans eſtate is perpetuall, he ſhall neither finally, nor to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally fall from this Rocke. The Diuell, that old de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuer, hath his wayes and means to attempt his ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, ſomtimes by fraud, ſomtimes by violence, now this way and then that way, but to no ſucceſſe: for the houſe of God is builded vpon <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Rock, &amp; euery <hi>Peter</hi> of this building, is ſo ſtrongly placed, that the gates of Hell ſhall not preuaile againſt him.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Thus farre you ſee that the Text is an alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory, the continuation of diuers Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors, which doe adorne and beautifie the place, but extend no further then a Metaphoricall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Here are diuers things compared; the Church of God, to a materiall temple: the elected members, to choice ſtones: the gathering
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19941:21"/>of the people of GOD by the Goſpell, preached with the inward aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, to building or raiſing of ſtones; the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> both God and man, to a great Rocke, whereupon you may ſuppoſe ſuch a Temple to be builded; the enemies of the Church, to the gates and munitions of Hell; their aſſaults againſt the <hi>Church</hi> and her members, to aſſaults and batteries againſt an inuincible fort ſtrongly builded vpon a Rocke, and for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable ſtrength thereof, bidding defiance to all her foes; the loſt labour of thoſe that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing againſt this ſtrong founded Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, to vaine and friuolous batteries. All this is either expreſſed or neceſſarily included.</p>
                  <p>Now, for as much as <hi>Peter</hi> truely beleeued, he was therefore as it were a ſtone of this ſtrong building, and becauſe he was choſen to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhip, he was therefore as it were a foundation ſtone, lying cloſe vpon the Rocke, for the ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of other ſtones to be laid vpon him. For by his Miniſtery many ſhould be conuerted to the faith, both <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and bee alſo edified in the ſame faith, by his doctrine: to the which doctrine euen the Biſhops and Elders of the Church ſhould referre themſelues, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by confirme the truth, confute errours, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themſelues to the Catholike doctrine and manners. Vpon the firſt reaſon that hee was a member of the Catholike Church, the gates of Hell could not preuaile againſt him: they might aſſault him, they might cauſe him to recoile; for Satan winnowed him, and preuailed ſo farre, that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19941:22"/>he denyed <hi>Chriſt:</hi> but they could not auaile to throw him vtterly from the Rocke, to his dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, or to ſeparate him wholly and for euer from the grace of God, which is to life eternall. Now, what <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi> he ſaith to euery true beleeuer, he is <hi>Peter,</hi> he is a ſtone of this buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and ſhall neuer finally periſh, becauſe hee hath builded him vpon himſelfe: for he hath ſaid,<hi>I will neuer leaue thee.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 13.5.</note> 
                     <hi>nor forſake thee.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Now all the furious winds of <hi>Aeolus,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>—<hi>velut agmine facto</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Qua data porta ruunt—</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q> the Diuell, and all the gates of Hell fight againſt the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and hence thoſe wars and rumors of warres, that fall vpon <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> like a mighty ſtorme, poſſeſſing the eares of men with the dolefull tidings of <hi>Cog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> armed compleatly to fight againſt the Saints of God. Will you know the euent of all theſe warres, conſpiracies, tumults, ſeditions, plagues? They beſiege an inuincible ſort, the gates of Hell ſhall not preuaile againſt it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mitylene,</hi> a magnificent Citie, was by the report of <hi>Vitrunius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itru. lib.</hi> 1.</note> rarely builded, but very badly ſituated. For when the South-wind bloweth, the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants grow ſicke: when the Weſt-wind, they cough: but when the North-wind doth blow, they are made well. The Church <hi>Militans</hi> is rarely builded, yet badly ſituated, as it were in the vnhealthy Mariſhes of <hi>Egypt;</hi> one while the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind bloweth, and it is ſicke: this is when Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies ſpring vp with the Goſpell, as tares among Wheat. You remember how ſicke the <hi>Church</hi> was of no leſſe then 80 Hereſies within the firſt 500
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19941:22"/>yeeres after <hi>Chriſt:</hi> you remember the growth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and power of the <hi>Arian</hi> and Papall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. Sometimes the Church cougheth and doth labour for life vnder the ſtrength of a diſeaſe; this is in time of tribulation, as in <hi>Egypt,</hi> in the <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> tranſportation; in thoſe ten bloody purſuites next following <hi>Chriſts</hi> aſcenſion: adde here the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> and Papall perſecutions. With this grieuous diſeaſe the <hi>Church</hi> is ſorely ſmitten at this time, and laboureth for life, being not altogether free from the languiſhing ill of Hereſies. This is the cough of the Lungs, a griefe very dangerous to the Patient, the poore diſtreſſed Spouſe of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> but God the Phyſician wil turne the wind, neuer doubt it, that it may be cured.</p>
               <p>It was <hi>Athanaſius</hi> reſolution in thoſe dayes of trouble, which <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata brought vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Saints of God, and when the Church of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria,</hi> whereof he was Biſhop, was compaſſed with a band of men: when the poore flocke of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſtood about him their Paſtour, with weeping teares, fearing on their owne behalfe, yet more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring on his: <hi>Nolite (inquit) ô filij, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>turbari,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rufim. Eccl. hiſt. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 34.</note> 
                  <hi>quia nube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula eſt, &amp; citò pertranſit.</hi> My little children, ſaith he, be not afraid, it is a little cloud, the wind wil diſpell it euen by and by. Some cloud hangeth ouer that Citie of God, the holy place of the Tabernacle of the moſt higheſt, and doeth for the preſent let fall an vnwholeſome raine vpon it, but the wind will turne about to the North to cure it, and the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies thereof ſhall miſſe their marke, becauſe the gates of Hell ſhall not preuaile againſt it. What can they doe more then God permitteth them to doe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19941:23"/>for the good of his <hi>Church</hi> and Choſen people? He that ſaid of that great <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Tyrant,
<note place="margin">2 Kings 19.28.</note> 
                  <hi>I will put my hooke in thy noſe, and my bridle in thy lips, and I will turne thee backe by the way by which thou cameſt;</hi> will alſo in good time put his hooke in their noſes, and his bridle in their lips, and will turne them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to their ruine; as the Tragedie of all perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in all ages ſhall witneſſe with me. But oh,
<q>
                     <l>Horrore quatior fata quo vergant timens,</l>
                     <l>Trepidum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> gemino pectus euentu labat!</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I ſee the bloody ſtripes of Confeſſors, their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and tortures; the cruell deaths of Martyres, their murthers, but cheries; the ſubuerſion of States, Common-weales, Kingdomes: Nation riſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Nation, and Kingdome againſt Kingdome. What can theſe things portend, but the vtter extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt? Anſw.</hi> Collect hence three things; Firſt, a purgation by a fiery tryall, of ſome particular places, where the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Goſpell of our Lord and Sauiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath been prophaned by Hereſies, by Schiſmes, or by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencious liuing. So fared it with <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> as you may read, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 36. from 11. to 22 verſe. And in this caſe, when I behold the bruiſed face of our neighbour Churches, States and Kingdomes, being not able to giue a reaſon of the preſent miſery, I am compelled to admire with the Apoſtle, ſaying, <hi>How vnſearchable are his Iudgements, and his wayes paſt finding out!</hi> Secondly, God will make his Church fruitfull by the blood of Martyrs and Confeſſors: For the Church is the Paradiſe or Garden of God, his people are his pleaſant plants; that his Garden may be fruitfull, he doth water it with blood.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:19941:23"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Sanguine fundata eſt Eccleſia, ſanguine creuit,</l>
                  <l>Sanguine ſuccreuit, ſanguine finis erit.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Who knowes not that the Church was founded in blood, the blood of the righteous <hi>Abel?</hi> that it had her increaſe in blood, the blood of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets? that it had her fulneſſe of ſtrength in blood, the blood of the Redeemer? and that it ſhall end in blood, the blood of the Martyrs? If therefore now at laſt a veine bee opened, and the Church doth bleed, after ſo many bloody battels, after ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny grieuous perſecutions, ſhall we at length ſtand amazed? To what end haue the Apoſtles of our Lord prepared vs vpon a reſolution, ſaying, that <hi>all that will liue godly in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.12.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall ſuffer perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> but that we ſhould bee ready alwayes to lay downe our neckes to the blowes of tyrants, and ſo much the rather, for that it is to the growth and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the Church of God? for <hi>Sanguis Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt ſemen Eccleſiae:</hi> the blood of the Martyrs is the ſeed of the Church. Laſtly, God will honour ſome of his ſeruants before other, as a King doth; and theſe ſhall weare the precious Robes of bonds, ſtripes, impriſonment, and death it ſelfe: for what greater honour to a Chriſtian, then to ſuffer for that bleſſed Name by which he is redeemed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It was ioy to the Apoſtles, that they were accounted worthie to ſuffer for the name of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Till therefore our Church come to be purged by that fyerie triall; or till our blood be ſhed, to water the garden of our God; or till the Lord will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour vs with the Crowne of Martyrdome: in the middeſt of theſe troubleſome dayes, as fellow-fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling members of that myſticall Body, of which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19941:24"/>Chriſt our Sauiour is the Head, we reſt conſtant and confident vpon that propheticall reſolution:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 46.1.</note> 
                  <hi>God is our hope, and ſtrength, a very preſent helpe in trouble. Therfore will wee not feare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2.</note> 
                  <hi>though the earth be reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and though the Mountaines be carried into the middeſt of the Sea:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3.</note> 
                  <hi>Though the waters thereof roare and be troubled, though the mountaines ſhake with the ſwelling thereof.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4.</note> 
                  <hi>There is a riuer, the ſtreames whereof ſhall make glad the Citie of God; the holy place of the Tabernacle of the moſt high.</hi> The Citie of God is his Church, watred with the ſtreames of the blood of the Redeemer, <hi>that Fountaine opened to the houſe of Dauid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zech. 13.1.</note> 
                  <hi>and to the inhabitants of Hieruſalem, for ſinne, and for vncleanneſſe.</hi> Seeing therefore that he hath taken vs into his protection, built vs on himſelfe, watered vs with his blood, it is enough for vs to commend our ſelues to his prouidence, and to reſt confident, that (becauſe we haue him for our Rock)
<q>
                     <l>Quatiat licèt</l>
                     <l>Orbem tumultus, terrá<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſedibus</l>
                     <l>Conuulſa, montium ruinis</l>
                     <l>Arctet aquas pelagi frementis;</l>
                     <l>The gates of Hell ſhall not preuaile againſt vs.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:19941:24"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
